Guide to the Kenya Collection
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Kenya collection
1901-2013
MS 1523
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
10.02
(19 boxes)
The collection consists of reports, printed material, and ephemera relating to the political, economic, and social conditions in Kenya. Also included are photographs.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Transferred from the African Collection Curator.
Associated Materials
African Collection (MS 605); Pamphlet Collection (MS 1351); African Postcard Collection (MS 1575). Manuscripts and Archives, Yale University Library.
Scope and Contents
The collection consists of reports, printed material, and ephemera relating to the political, economic, and social conditions in Kenya. Also included are photographs.
Arrangement
The material in the original accession is arranged chronologically, with photographs last. Additions to the collection may vary in arrangement.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Kikuyu (African people); Women -- Kenya; Great Britain -- Foreign relations -- Kenya; Kenya -- Description and travel; Kenya -- Economic conditions; Kenya -- Foreign relations -- Great Britain; Kenya -- Intellectual life; Kenya -- Politics and government -- 1963-1978; Kenya -- Politics and government -- 1978-2002; Kenya -- Politics and government -- To 1963; Kenya -- Social conditions; Photographs -- Kenya; Mboya, Tom; Odinga, Ajuma Oginga, 1911-1994; UMOJA (Political organization: London, England)
- Inventory
  - Printed material concerning relations with Great Britain: includes colonial papers, 1915-1954 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - East African Indian National Congress: addresses, resolutions, reports, 1938-1950 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Academic journals and newsletters, 1961-1992 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Political organizations: documents; journals; printed material; reports, 1961-1992, undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Economic magazines; reports; journals, 1963-1980 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Economic magazines; reports; journals, 1991-1992 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Magazines; periodicals; news bulletins, 1963-1992 (Box 1, Folder 7 - 8)
  - General information pamphlets; brochures; booklets, 1966-1985 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Women's movement/organizations, 1966-1993 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Government papers: documents; journals; printed material; reports, 1968-1993, undated (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Institute of Current World Affairs: printed material, 1970-1989 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - "The Marsabit Experiment": posters used to convey health messages, produced by UNICEF, 1976-1978 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Newspapers, 1977-1994 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Newspaper clippings: miscellaneous, 1980-1988 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - University of Nairobi: reports and papers, 1980-1991 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Committee for the Release of Political Prisoners in Kenya: newsletters; release bulletins, 1982-1992 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Elections: reports; bulletins; memorabilia, 1983-1993 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - "Habari: Bulletin of the Embassy of the Federal Republic of Germany", 1983-1984 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - "The Trial of Dedan Kimathi": theater program, 1984 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - United Movement for Democracy in Kenya (UMOJA): printed material, 1987-1989 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Kenyatta University: seminar papers, 1988-1990 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Ministry of Foreign Affairs and International Cooperation: news bulletins, 1989-1993 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Labour Party Democracy (L.P.D.): press releases, 1992 (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - "On the Present Situation in Our Country": pastoral letter of the Catholic Bishops of Kenya, Undated (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - "Tom Mboya, Underdevelopment, and I," by Ali A. Mazrui: essay by professor of political science at Makere University College (Kampula, Kenya), Undated (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Tana Lake: photograph, Undated (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - "Uganda Railway Shoot": photograph album/journal, 1909 (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - Photograph album, [1930?] (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - Colonial life: stereoscopic photographs, Undated (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - East Africa: photograph album by E. Gladden, [1962?-1968?] (Box 4, Folder 31)
- Additional Material, Accession 1995-M-047
  - "The Undugu Story," by Ezra Mbogori: booklet about the street children of Nairobi and Father Arnold Grol's rehabilitation program, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - "Jaramogi Oginga Odinga: the Passing of a Hero": memorial tribute, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Additional Material, Accession 1995-M-130
  - Correspondence pertaining to the grave of the Duke of Aosta, Italian viceroy, 1948 (Box 1)
  - Additional printed materials, 1901-1909, 1943-1948, 1962-1963, 1979, 1994-1997, undated (Box 1)
  - Photograph album of F.W. Brett [private secretary to governor of Kenya from 1912-1915], 1932 (Box 2)
  - Travel diary of Mrs. R. Hepburn [includes photographs], 1932 (Box 3)
  - Photograph album [World War II] (Box 4)
- Additional Material, Accession 1999-M-012
  - Additional printed material, 1907-1933, 1939-1963, 1997 (Box 1)
- Additional Material, Accession 2000-M-022
  - Additional printed materials, 1967, 1970, 1977, 1985, 1993, 1997, undated (Box 1)
- Additional Material, Accession 2002-M-081
  - "Reports on the Kikuyu," by Jeanne M. Fisher [carbon typescript], Volume I, reports 1-4, [195-?] (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - "Reports on the Kikuyu," Volume II, reports 5-6 [bound in reverse order], [1950-?] (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Flyers promoting the "Free Jomo Kenyatta" appeal, 1957 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - "Report of the Mombasa Municipality Commission", 1919 May (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Miscellaneous printed materials, 1987, undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Additional Material, Accession 2004-M-040
  - Booklets
    - "Conflict and Nationhood" (The Africa Bureau), 1963 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - "Kenya, What are the facts?" (Communist Party, London), 1953 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - "Mau Mau" (Church Missionary Society, London), 1952 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - "Release the Political Prisoners in Kenya" (Committee for the Release of Political Prisoners in Kenya), 1983 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Election material [pictures of candidate, flag, visor], 2003 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Selected periodicals [listing of random issues of individual titles in the box], 1962, 1963, 1975-1987 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Additional Material, Accession 2006-M-033
  - African Medical and Research Foundation (AMRF) and East African Flying Doctor Services, newsletter, no. 12, 1977 May (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - "Development Agenda", 1989 June (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Goethe Institut Nairobi, Jambo Umlaut, no. 5, 1992 January-July (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Historical Association of Kenya, newsletter, minutes from 1985 annual general meeting, 1982, 1983, 1985 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Kenya Woman, special issue on the death of Mzee Jomo Kenyatta, [1978] (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Nairobi Weekly Observer, 1992 December 4, 25 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Operation Firimbi, The Campaign Against Public-land Grabbing in Kenya, "Firimbi," no.1, 1999 May (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - "Wajibu, Social Change: Are Women Actors or Spectators?" vol. 3, no. 2, 1988 July-August (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Za Achikumbi, 1996 November-December (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Additional Material, Accession 2010-M-073
  Arrangement
  The material is arranged as received from the source.
  - Printed material
    - Afrika ya Kesho, Undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Val Fajr, 1986 Nov/Dec, 1988 Apr/May (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Tembo Times, 1986 March (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Undugu Society of Kenya: Annual Report for the year, 1982 December (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Sauti ya Kericho, 1980 September 19 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Sauti ya Meru, 1981 April 2 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Kenya National Council of Social Service (Sharing Approaches at Work), 1985 October 1 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Map and Guide: the streets of Mombasa Island, Undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Campaign ephemera for Mwai Kibaki, Undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Photographs
    - Photographs of Jomo Kenyatta, prime minister and president of Kenya, 1961-1964, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Additional material, 1962-2000s; Accession 2015-M-001
  - Printed material and photographs, 1962-1998, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Printed fabric sample, Circa 1971 (Box 2)
  - Posters, Circa 2000s (Box 3)